<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources: Division of Lands and Minerals, Mineral Potential Evaluation Section</origin><pubdate>20140723</pubdate><title>Aggregate Resource Mapping Program - Compilation of Geologic Field Observations</title><pubinfo><publish>Minnesota DNR - Lands and Minerals</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/completed/index.html</onlink></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>This spatial dataset of geologic field observations is based on a compilation of GIS aggregate resources (sand and gravel, crushed stone) reconnaissance scale data spanning twenty county projects completed over a number of years (1987-present) by the DNR's Aggregate Resource Mapping Program (ARMP). The attribute data available varies as a result of the varied years of completion and changes in databases structure and verbiage over time. The past project GIS data has been loaded into the current file geodatabase used by the Aggregate Resource Mapping Program. Therefore the data from the most recent completed counties (Aitkin, Stearns, Kanabec, Olmsted) have the most complete attribute table, while the earlier mapped counties (Sherburne, Wright, Isanti) have limited attribute data. Digital Geologic Field Observations started being collected for the Isanti County Project completed in 1991 and continues today. 

This dataset includes information gathered in the field by Aggregate Mapping Resource Program geologists since 1991.  It includes 15,957 field observation sites in Minnesota. Observations include, but are not limited to: natural exposures of surficial geologic sediment or bedrock outcrops, artificial and temporary exposures in gravel, borrow, sand pits, or quarries, along road cuts or in excavations and observations of the surface. This spatial dataset may contain a field description of each site, the dominant type of materials encountered, the source of information, geologic unit thickness (if non-aggregate-bearing; aggregate unit thickness and geologic overburden thickness if aggregate is not present at surface). </abstract><purpose>To summarize the geologic field observations collected in Minnesota from a compilation of GIS aggregate resources (sand and gravel, crushed stone) reconnaissance scale data spanning twenty county projects completed over a number of years (1991-present). These field observations were made to confirm air photo, topographic map, Digital Elevation Model, and soil map interpretations that identified potential aggregate- bearing landforms.

About the Aggregate Resource Mapping Program:
The Aggregate Resource Mapping Program (ARMP) began in 1984 when the Minnesota Legislature passed a law (Minnnesota Statutes, section 84.94) to: Identify and classify aggregate resources out side of the Twin Cities metropolitan area; Give aggregate resource information to local units of government and others for making comprehensive land-use and zoning plans; Introduce aggregate resource protection; and Promote orderly and environmentally sound development of the resource.
Aggregate Mapping Home Page: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/index.html
Aggregate Mapping Methodology: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/methodology.html</purpose><supplinf>State of Minnesota</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><sngdate><caldate>20210328</caldate></sngdate></timeinfo><current>Data were collected between 1991 and 2020.</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Continually</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-97.23</westbc><eastbc>-89.53</eastbc><northbc>49.37</northbc><southbc>43.5</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>field observations, geology, aggregate mapping program, sand and gravel, bedrock outcrops</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>None</accconst><useconst>Use Disclaimer: 
Every reasonable effort has been made to ensure the accuracy of the factual data on which this map interpretation is based. However, the Department of Natural Resources does not warrant the accuracy, completeness, or any implied uses of these data. Users may wish to verify critical information; sources include both the references here and information on file in the offices of the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources. Every effort has been made to ensure the interpretation shown conforms to sound geologic and cartographic principles. No claim is made that the interpretation shown is rigorously correct, however, and it should not be used to guide engineering-scale decisions without site-specific verification. This information should not be used to establish legal title, boundaries, or locations of improvements.

Data Disclaimer
The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources makes no representation or warranties, express or implied, with respect to the reuse of data provided herewith, regardless of its format or the means of its transmission. There is no guarantee or representation to the user as to the accuracy, currency, suitability, or reliability of this data for any purpose. The user accepts the data 'as is', and assumes all risks associated with its use. By accepting this data, the user agrees not to transmit this data or provide access to it or any part of it to another party unless the user shall include with the data a copy of this disclaimer. The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources assumes no responsibility for actual or consequential damage incurred as a result of any user's reliance on this data.</useconst><browse><browsen>http://images.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate/fobs_image.jpg</browsen></browse><crossref><citeinfo><title>Other Compiled Aggregate Mapping GIS Datasets: 
Sand and Gravel Resource Potential; Crushed Stone Resource Potential; Geologic Field Observationsl; Test Holes; and Status Map of Completed, In-Progress, and Requested Projects

List of Completed DNR Aggregate Mapping Project's Web Pages to Download Maps and Original GIS Data and Metadata at:
http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/completed/index.html
Aitkin County (2014) 
Stearns County (2012)
Kanabec County (2012)
Portions of Northern St. Louis and Northern Lake Counties (2010)
Olmsted County (2010)
Carlton County and Fond du Lac Reservation (2009)
Mille Lacs County (2007)
Meeker County (2006)
Renville County (2003)
Le Sueur County (2003)
Itasca County (2003) - Contracted with MGS
Benton County (2002)
Dodge County (2002)
Chisago County (2000) - Contracted with MGS
Nicollet County (1999)
Blue Earth County (1999)
Clay County (1995)
Isanti County (1991)
Wright County (1989)
Sherburne County (1987)

Completed MGS Aggregate Endowment of the 7-County Twin Cities Metropolitan Area
7-County Mapping Web page: Information and links to view and download report, maps, and original GIS data and metadata for this MGS mapping project.</title></citeinfo></crossref><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Lands and Minerals</cntorg><cntper>James Olson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailling and Physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Rd</address><city>Saint Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5429</cntvoice><cntemail>james.olson@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataqual><complete>The data is as complete as when the county project was completed. </complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>See lineage</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>None</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>This varies since the data is a compilation of points collected between 1991-2013. Please consult the original project metadata found at the Aggregate Mapping Program's completed project page at: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/completed/index.html  

For counties completed after 2006 the points were edited in the field with a GPS (+/- 3 Meters), tablet PC, and ArcGIS Desktop. For counties completed prior to 2006 points were penciled in on printed USGS 1:24,000 quadrangle maps and later digitized on screen using GIS software.</procdesc></procstep></lineage></dataqual><eainfo><overview><eaover>This dataset consists of geologic field observations such as; site type, material type, field description, material thickness and overburden, sampling, county, and year. Much of this information is not available for Counties completed prior to 1999. After 2005 the attribute data stays pretty consistent.

An example attribute table with descriptions for field observations is provided here from the Kanabec County Aggregate Map:
http://files.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate/aggregate_fobs_attribute_example_kanabeccounty.pdf

If you need more information please consult the original project data and metadata found at the Aggregate Mapping Program's completed project page at: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/completed/index.html  </eaover></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab><stdorder><ordering>Visit the web site noted in the online linkage section, or send an email to the Distribution Contact listed in this metadata record</ordering></stdorder><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota DNR - GIS</cntorg><cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Rd</address><city>Saint Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice><cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20210328</metd><metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn><metstdv>1.2</metstdv><metextns><onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink></metextns><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Lands and Minerals</cntorg><cntper>James Olson</cntper></cntperp><cntpos>GIS Analyst</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype><address>500 Lafayette Rd</address><city>Saint Paul</city><state>MN</state><postal>55155</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>651-259-5429</cntvoice><cntemail>james.olson@state.mn.us</cntemail></cntinfo></metc></metainfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>15</utmzone></utm></gridsys><planci><plandu>meters</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>NAD83</horizdn><ellips>GRS80</ellips></geodetic></horizsys></spref></metadata>