<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Minnesota Department of Natural Resources (DNR)</origin>
        <pubdate>20140723</pubdate>
        <title>Aggregate Resource Mapping Program</title>
        <pubinfo>
          <publish>Minnesota DNR - Lands and Minerals</publish>
        </pubinfo>
        <onlink>http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/completed/index.html</onlink>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The Aggregate Resource Mapping Program (ARMP) began in 1984 when the Minnesota Legislature passed a law (Minnnesota Statutes, section 84.94) to: 
- Identify and classify aggregate resources outside of the Twin Cities metropolitan area; 
- Give aggregate resource information to local units of government and others for making comprehensive land-use and zoning plans; 
- Introduce aggregate resource protection; and Promote orderly and environmentally sound development of the resource.

Provided here is a compilation of GIS data produced by the DNR's Aggregate Resource Mapping Program.  Also provided is the aggregate resource GIS data from the 7-County Metropolitan Area mapped by the Minnesota Geological Survey (MGS). Please see the layer-specific metadata for each of the 9 layers for more details:

&lt;b&gt;ARMP:&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;a href='armp_aggmines.html' target=_blank&gt;Compilation of Gravel Pits, Quarries, and Prospects&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href='armp_crushedstonepotential.html' target=_blank&gt;Compilation of Crushed Stone Resource Potential&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href='armp_fieldobservations.html' target=_blank&gt;Compilation of Geologic Field Observations&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href='armp_sandandgravelpotential.html' target=_blank&gt;Compilation of Sand and Gravel Resource Potential&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href='dnr_testholes.html' target=_blank&gt;Compilation of DNR Test Holes&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href='projects_and_status.html' target=_blank&gt;Status Map&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;b&gt;7-County Metro Area:&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;a href='mgs_sevencounty_aggmines.html' target=_blank&gt;Compilation of Pits and Quarries&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href='mgs_sevencounty_crushedstone.html' target=_blank&gt;Bedrock Aggregate Sources&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href='mgs_sevencounty_sandandgravel.html' target=_blank&gt;Sand and Gravel Sources&lt;/a&gt;
</abstract>
      <purpose>About the Aggregate Resource Mapping Program:
The Aggregate Resource Mapping Program (ARMP) began in 1984 when the Minnesota Legislature passed a law (Minnnesota Statutes, section 84.94) to: Identify and classify aggregate resources out side of the Twin Cities metropolitan area; Give aggregate resource information to local units of government and others for making comprehensive land-use and zoning plans; Introduce aggregate resource protection; and Promote orderly and environmentally sound development of the resource.
Aggregate Mapping Home Page: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/index.html
Aggregate Mapping Methodology: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/methodology.html</purpose>
      <supplinf>State of Minnesota</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <sngdate>
          <caldate>20230203</caldate>
        </sngdate>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Time Period of Content date indicates the date which the user can be confident of accuracy and completeness of the dataset.</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>Continually</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-97.23</westbc>
        <eastbc>-89.53</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.37</northbc>
        <southbc>43.5</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekey>Aggregate Resource Mapping Program, gravel pit, Sand pit, quarry, crushed stone, sand and gravel, Aggregate Source Information System (ASIS), bedrock, geological characteristics, aggregate potential, construction aggregates, field observations, geology, aggregate mapping program, bedrock outcrops, surficial geology, probability, quality, test hole drilling, aggregate quality, sieve, gradations, aggregate resources, sand and gravel pits, quarries, mgs, M-102, bedrock sources, construction aggregate potential</themekey>
        <themekt>
          </themekt>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekey>Minnesota, seven-county metropolitan area, twin cities</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>Use Disclaimer: 
Every reasonable effort has been made to ensure the accuracy of the factual data on which this map interpretation is based. However, the Department of Natural Resources does not warrant the accuracy, completeness, or any implied uses of these data. Users may wish to verify critical information; sources include both the references here and information on file in the offices of the Minnesota Department of Natural Resources. Every effort has been made to ensure the interpretation shown conforms to sound geologic and cartographic principles. No claim is made that the interpretation shown is rigorously correct, however, and it should not be used to guide engineering-scale decisions without site-specific verification. This information should not be used to establish legal title, boundaries, or locations of improvements.

Data Disclaimer
The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources makes no representation or warranties, express or implied, with respect to the reuse of data provided herewith, regardless of its format or the means of its transmission. There is no guarantee or representation to the user as to the accuracy, currency, suitability, or reliability of this data for any purpose. The user accepts the data 'as is', and assumes all risks associated with its use. By accepting this data, the user agrees not to transmit this data or provide access to it or any part of it to another party unless the user shall include with the data a copy of this disclaimer. The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources assumes no responsibility for actual or consequential damage incurred as a result of any user's reliance on this data.</useconst>
    <browse>
      <browsen>https://images.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate/status_image.jpg</browsen>
    </browse>
    <crossref>
      <citeinfo>
        <title>List of Completed DNR Aggregate Mapping Project's Web Pages to Download Maps and Original GIS Data and Metadata at:
http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/completed/index.html
Kandiyohi County (2021)
Aitkin County (2014) 
Stearns County (2012)
Kanabec County (2012)
Portions of Northern St. Louis and Northern Lake Counties (2010)
Olmsted County (2010)
Carlton County and Fond du Lac Reservation (2009)
Mille Lacs County (2007)
Meeker County (2006)
Renville County (2003)
Le Sueur County (2003)
Itasca County (2003) - Contracted with MGS
Benton County (2002)
Dodge County (2002)
Chisago County (2000) - Contracted with MGS
Nicollet County (1999)
Blue Earth County (1999)
Clay County (1995)
Isanti County (1991)
Wright County (1989)
Sherburne County (1987)

Completed MGS Aggregate Endowment of the 7-County Twin Cities Metropolitan Area
7-County Mapping Web page: Information and links to view and download report, maps, and original GIS data and metadata for this MGS mapping project.</title>
      </citeinfo>
    </crossref>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Lands and Minerals</cntorg>
          <cntper>James Olson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Analyst</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>Mailling and Physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5429</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>james.olson@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>
      </logic>
    <complete>
      </complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>
          </horizpar>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>
          </vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>This varies since the data is a compilation of gravel pits, sand pits, borrow pits, quarries, and prospects collected between 1987-2013. Please consult the original project metadata found at the Aggregate Mapping Program's completed project page at: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/lands_minerals/aggregate_maps/completed/index.html  

Generally speaking, these data points were captured from several different digital GIS data sources at the time of mapping, including USGS 1:24000 quadrangles, 1:12000 USGS DOQs (from 1991), Farm Service Agency (FSA) color air photos (from 2003-04, 2005, 2006, 2008, 2009, 2010), Natural Resource Conservation Service Soil Survey point data, and the ASIS (Aggregate Source Information System) dataset from the Minnesota Department of Transportation. 

For counties completed after 2006 the points were edited in the field with a GPS (+/- 3 Meters), tablet PC, and ArcGIS Desktop. For counties completed prior to 2006 points were penciled in on printed USGS 1:24,000 quadrangle maps and later digitized on screen using GIS software.</procdesc>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>
        </attraccr>
    </attracc>
  </dataqual>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <gridsys>
          <gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn>
          <utm>
            <utmzone>15</utmzone>
          </utm>
        </gridsys>
        <planci>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>NAD83</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS80</ellips>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <resdesc>geos_aggregate_mapping</resdesc>
    <distliab>The Minnesota Department of Natural Resources General Geographic Data License Agreement is online: http://www.dnr.state.mn.us/sitetools/data_software_license.html</distliab>
    <stdorder>
      <ordering>Visit the web site noted in the online linkage section, or send an email to the Distribution Contact listed in this metadata record</ordering>
    </stdorder>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota DNR - GIS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Zeb Thomas</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Data Systems Coordinator</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5637</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>zeb.thomas@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20210328</metd>
    <metstdn>Minnesota Geographic Metadata Guidelines</metstdn>
    <metstdv>1.2</metstdv>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.mngeo.state.mn.us/committee/standards/mgmg/metadata.htm</onlink>
    </metextns>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>Minnesota DNR - Lands and Minerals</cntorg>
          <cntper>James Olson</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntpos>GIS Analyst</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical</addrtype>
          <address>500 Lafayette Rd</address>
          <city>Saint Paul</city>
          <state>MN</state>
          <postal>55155</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>651-259-5429</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>james.olson@state.mn.us</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
